last time we discussed the basics of
composition the rule of thirds and
simple shape language to design our
panels
David Fincher and welcome back to my
course on creating the comic book page
as the artist we want to visualize the
story unfolding from panel to panel in
the most compelling and engaging way
possible composing each panel the way
cinematographer might plan shots for a
movie using different lenses in varying
camera placement to more effectively
tell the story and how we position the
camera for the reader's point of view
can have a major impact on the way the
reader experiences the story if you want
to follow along with me as we design our
own comic page head on over to proco.com
comic page and sign up for the course
we'll have more lessons and go much
further in depth into what we learned
here we'll be posting premium episodes
regularly so I hope to see you there all
right let's get started
I've sketched in three panels and in the
first panel I'm going to use my rule of
thirds and I'm going to draw a figure
pretty small on my panel
my upper third just to kind of fill it
out I'll draw some trees and some
background there's a very simple
representation of the panel and this is
what we would call an establishing shot
or a long shot and in this panel we can
see the figure we can see the whole
background around the figure it slows
our pacing a little bit and it serves to
showcase our figure but also the
background around the figure so we
really get a sense of the environment
that that figure exists in but we don't
get anywhere near as much a sense of
what that figure is about whether
thinking or what they're feeling and
what they're doing so from here we're
going to move into a medium close-up and
in this shot we can see much more of our
figure but we can still see some
background and in a medium close-up we
can see not only the face and much more
of the expression that our character has
but we can also see what they're doing
with their hands and while it showcases
some of our background it does a much
better job of showcasing our figure
in our last example we're going to move
into a close-up of our figure's head we
can move into a close-up or really an
extreme close-up extreme close-up
close-up lean to an eye or it can be a
hand or whatever it is that you want to
showcase and using close-ups really
allows us to focus in on our character
and see subtlety that we really can't
see from a greater distance
and these three shots working in
conjunction with each other give you a
sense of your environment in a long shot
then move in on the characters for
action and so we can see a better sense
of what our characters are doing and
then in extreme close-ups we really get
a strong sense of exactly what our
characters are thinking and get a much
better sense of what they're all about
and you'll notice if you read comic
books or watch movies that you'll always
see a shot whether it's at the beginning
of a scene the end of the scene or the
middle of the scene where we really pull
out so we can see the environment that
our characters exist within then we move
in on the characters and then we move
even closer so we get a real sense of
the emotion behind the scene
finally we need to talk about point of
view in my first panel I'm going to be
looking up at my figure and so I'm going
to see the figure from below which means
that I've got a horizon line that's well
below my panel and that would represent
my eye line my viewer is actually
looking up at the figure when you choose
a low angle and you look up at a figure
or a building or an object it makes that
building object or figure large and
imposing and even looming and for a
powerful hero or for a villain it's a
very effective technique to make them
look Larger than Life in my next panel
we're going to do the exact opposite and
we're going to be well above our figure
and we're going to be looking down at
them and it's essentially the same
figure just drawn from a different angle
and it makes them look diminished and a
little smaller and it's a way to make a
figure look maybe even oppressed or sad
and it's something that psychologically
can have an impact even if they don't
understand that you're using these
techniques to Garner that reaction our
last example is a profile and it's a
straight on shot and it gives us a very
stoic solid Wyatt kind of a panel not
only is it important to know that you
can create a different emotional impact
using different angles but it also helps
to vary your storytelling so you don't
have the same shot from panel to panel
to panel which can become very boring
hi David's course is currently 20 off
for the Black Friday sale go to
proco.com comic page and use the code
black20 to get the discount and so an
example of a page done that way what I
have here is a perfectly serviceable
page it works the storytelling can flow
but it is outrageously boring and so
let's do that same page again and I'm
going to start with the same panel that
I did in the first version It's a medium
shot of my figure and now in my second
panel I'm going to show my other figure
and I'm going to zoom in much closer so
I get a much bigger shot of his face and
see subtlety that we really can't see
from a greater distance
and now in my third panel I'm going to
show both figures I'm going to show them
from above figure's got his arms crossed
my other figure is looking at him
gesturing very quickly drawn just to
establish my figures on the page
and so for this one I've pulled out it's
a much longer shot and I can see my
background around them whatever it
happens to be and now in my last panel
I'm going to come in behind this
character's head maybe I'll even
silhouette it and we'll see our first
character and so we get a two shot like
this and you can see that in this
example I've changed up my sizing quite
a bit more I have just a medium shot
here and then I've closed in much more
with a larger head and now I've zoomed
out much more here and moved my camera
so you're looking at the scene from
above and it gives you a different
perspective and just changes things up
and then in the last panel I've
silhouetted a head in the foreground and
included both figures in the scene while
focusing on my original first figure
and it just makes it a lot more visually
interesting and you really want to think
in terms of this for all of your pages
you want to move the camera around zoom
in zoom out you want to have bigger
shots smaller shots and juxtapose those
with each other to keep things more
visually interesting and now there's one
other major Pitfall that's very easy to
run into with your storytelling if
you're not aware of it going in and that
is the 180 Rule and all that is from
overhead I'm going to draw a line and
I'm going to draw an arc around that
line just about like this and what this
line represents is the limit of where I
can put my camera now I can put this
line anywhere but generally speaking you
want to keep it to one side of whatever
it is that you're showing and so that
means that I can put the camera here and
look at the scene this way I can put it
here anywhere along here and really it's
not just a line you can call it like a
half a sphere here's my figure and so I
could visualize My Scene all the way
from the ground all the way from the top
what I want to avoid though is putting
the camera over here
and so let's take a look at how that
works by drawing a couple of panels and
so in panel one I've got my two figures
I'm looking at it from about this level
and I'm looking directly into the scene
and I could have chosen for this first
panel any Viewpoint I wanted I could
have went directly from the top all the
way to the floor it really doesn't
matter but the point is that I've picked
an angle once I've drawn my first panel
and to make this easier I'm going to
make one character light and another
character dark just so we can track the
characters as they go into the next
panel now in my next panel I'm going to
draw my same two figures again and now
this character is dark this character is
light so what's happened from above I
was viewing the scene from this side
this Arc and what I did is I just moved
the camera over here and so visually
what you see is a flipping of your
characters it looks like characters have
just instantly moved in the scene as
opposed to just moving the camera
yeah if you want more lessons from David
check out his course at proco.com
comicpage where he teaches a whole lot
of stuff about comic book penciling
shading inking and composition it's a
master class on comic making from start
to finish hope to see you there
[Music]