two key elements to I would say every
single page if you can do it is to have
a full shot of a character who's in the
panel and a good shot of their
environment everything else on this page
cannot show full body Wolverine or
background like this panel can be a
closeup of Wolverine angry but as long
as you've got that first panel here of
the full body and the full background it
just sets the tone for the whole world
for the whole page I recently was
talking to a guy who had me look through
his portfolio and the cartooning was
really nice but a lot of the panels
didn't have any background in them you
need some backgrounds in here he came
back to me with those same pages with
backgrounds improved it greatly and if
you don't want to draw a full body shot
what are you drawing comics for anyways
that's the fun stuff and learning art
and storytelling with Comics should be
fun too at pro.com Marvel we're making
fun lessons teaching you how to make
awesome art and learning how to tell
stories like professional in the
industry so come check it out and the
thing is this is Comics too so you want
to have that action you want to have
that excitement in there and you know
sometimes a background can slow that
down a little bit it's okay to leave the
background out at times if it's a creepy
mad scientist these are going to work
better than a background on some level
they are some sort of background but
they also like give mood and and
atmosphere and portray what's happening
where we need it all to you know you can
occasionally let's say here you can do
some fun stuff with like panels that
look a lot alike let's say before
Wolverine went into battle here he had
to sneeze I mean you can see here these
are very similar panels it works within
the Dynamics of the page but you don't
want to do 10 panels like
this even with this basic structure on a
page you can do so much you could have a
close-up shot a guy walking down an
alley over the shoulder people talking
you could do from down below now you can
even come back to another closeup of the
other guy's face this could be like
another dude he's angry goes throw a
punch punch comes in the panel guy
Dodges it and if you need to do it this
way start out making Comics this way
just make a nine panel grid and do it
that way as the dialogue of making
Comics starts to develop itself in your
brain you'll eventually get to this but
if you need to start this way to learn
there's nothing wrong with that even
professional dudes draw this way Jack
Kirby one of the most amazing comic book
artists of all time he's done some
amazing battle sequences that were
worked in the nine panel grid if that's
what helps you out starting that way
then I would say do it all the way it's
a great system it helps you learn the
language of making Comics it takes a
little bit of the pressure off of having
to think about making it this dynamic
because this can be dynamic too like I
said you got head you got a awesome face
shot you got an alley you got over the
shoulders you got down below you got
another head you got a punch being
thrown this guy's avoiding the punch
he's running away and then let's what do
we want for last panel trips over a pipe
and there you go hopefully we'll
progress into doing this but even that
is fun I mean look at that we got this
panel Wolverine's running it's cold
outside he sneezes he gets mad and I
don't know he's trying to cut the tree
down cuz he sneezed but then you got the
whole page like right next to it and
let's say this cuts to the past or
something who knows but then you've got
this panel it's 9 panel grid it sets it
apart from what this is and those two
pages look fun together as the artist
that I am I am trying to utilize every
space on the page that I possibly can
cuz it's all awesome real estate I mean
even if you look at this here so I got
Wolverine running through the snow right
this hand coming out into this panel
like almost tells the reader exactly
where they need to go there are times
when you don't want to use it you know
like this page here it's probably not
any of these panels I can really see
going into another panel you might do
something like even to make the nine
panel grid a little bit more Dynamic
let's say the panel is mainly about this
guy I just did you could put him and his
shoulders are going off the page here
and he's like oh my gosh cuz the main
point of this page was to show that he
was sad about or scared about something
if you look at it like look you're still
on that nine panel grid really giving it
a little bit something extra that you
don't normally see in the nine panel
grid makes it like that much more
exciting and such a fun page to look at
but he's not breaking into any other
panels to be honest we just pulled the
panels away from him you wouldn't want
like Wolverine's fins to go out here
this keeps it like nice and tight and
clean here you're going to find your
moments and you're going to see where
you got little spaces that you can like
bring it over into and it's just all
about that Dynamic comic making and I
think it just really really gives it
that little extra you know when you look
at a page or whatever and something's
going a little bit more into that other
page panel every page is almost a little
Cliffhanger cuz you do you want
everybody to turn the page to the next
page so let's say in the in the middle
of this page you've got a guy picking
his nose you could do four panels of the
guy picking his nose you could have he's
thinking about picking his nose his hand
starts to go up right then you've got
another panel shot picking his nose and
then we got the last panel got a nice
gooey booger I mean that this is the fun
of comics you know know he's got an ice
gooey booger you could also just use
these two panels you know to do the same
thing you know what I'm saying like you
got this and this finger going up booger
coming out like I said this is this is
pacing in comics this is like what do I
choose to do and and that's the fun
about making Comics I think like I like
I like to do stuff like this where it's
like it's like a slow little animation
of that but you know sometimes you don't
have room on the pap P to do that and
sometimes you might send it back to the
writer or editor and they're like Aaron
we don't need that many panels of the
guy picking his nose and I'm just like
oh man it's really fun to draw that guy
picking his nose you know but whatever
but yeah you could do like I said you
can just do the two panels and give it
the same effect and the writer might
only have written two panels of guy
picking his nose maybe this guy who was
picking his nose here like hanging out
in front of a convenience store no what
you didn't show was that like
galatis and The Watcher are like
fighting and he's down here he's just a
little guy convenience store right and
just add a little love to the story then
we close up on him he was picking his
nose and then the Watcher punches
Galactus and then Galactus falls down
onto the convenience store and that's a
lot of stuff you got to show on that
page so maybe having four panels of the
guy picking his nose is not your best
idea but also we've got a lot of
exciting things happening and the pacing
of this slows it down just a notch and
then you're right back in the action and
boom and that's pacing in comics and
like you know there was a there's one of
my favorite scenes in a comic where
somebody has just died in this comic and
the character is really sad and there's
six panels the character standing there
bop boop raindrops falling around him
also in those panels the colorist did
cool things cuz there was cop cars
around so the cop the lights were
shining differently then you get to this
panel same shot still and all of a
sudden you see somebody else come in
from this side and they've got a jacket
in their hand and this panel here the
guy is putting the jacket on it helping
him out and then this panel here walking
out of the shot and the guy who brought
him the jacket is walking away too once
again some you might consider this a
boring page but to see something slowly
play out out like this in comics is
always nice too you could do it with two
panels we could have probably done this
whole thing in four panels but I think
doing it in six just that little bit
more pacing gives it that little bit
more like time to breathe time to let
the characters live the thing is if
you're going to make comics the story is
the most important thing you can be a
bad artist and still tell a good story
you can draw Pinups of Captain America
Spider-Man and whoever all day long but
to be an actual like comic maker you
have to take this writer script and put
it down on paper the reader has to
follow that and know what's happening on
any moment after this check out the rest
of the lessons in Marvel's The Art of
Storytelling course we've got working
Marvel artists showing you how we make
comics with stepbystep structured
lessons some secret behind the-scenes
stuff and assignments to test and expand
your skills hop into the world of comics
and learn to create your own atpro /m
Marvel